RG 019, Department of Social Services
Connecticut State Library
Department of Social Services records
1775-1959
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Dept. of Social Services
9.5 cubic feet
The Department of Social Services provides a broad range of services to the elderly, persons with disabilities, families, and individuals who need assistance in maintaining or achieving their full potential for self-direction, self-reliance and independent living.
RG019
Multiple
Historical Note
The Department of Social Services provides assistance to families and individuals through programs such as child-care block grants, energy assistance, vocational rehabilitation, refugee assistance, programs for the elderly, temporary assistance for needy families, food stamps, Section 8 housing vouchers, and the state child support enforcement plan. The Department has evolved through several titles that reflect the changes in public policy toward those citizens in need: State Board of Charities was established in 1873; name changed to Commission on Public Welfare in 1919; in 1921 name changed to Department of Public Welfare; 1935, name changed to Public Welfare Council; Office of the Commissioner of Public Welfare was established in 1935; 1953, name changed to State Welfare Department and the Welfare Commissioner; 1975, name changed to Department of Social Services; in 1979 Social Services split in two. The direct successor agency is the Department of Income Maintenance, which retains the same Commissioner and Statutory authority as Social Services. The other is the Department of Human Resources. In 1993 the Department of Social Services reformed by merger of: Department of Income Maintenance, Department of Human Resources, and Department on Aging.
See also the.
Scope and Content
Series 1. State Board of Charities contain letter books, 1883-1901, and registers of state paupers accounts that predate the board, 1809-1824 and ledgers created by the Board and subsequent agencies, 1877-1917. Series 2. Public Welfare Council contains one report to the General Assembly, 1947. Series 3. Welfare Department contains minutes of meetings of the boards through the public welfare council, 1893-1951; a secretary's diary, 1893-1922; several reports and a Master's thesis, and records of the Litchfield County Temporary Home, 1908-1915; and the New Haven County Temporary Home, 1899-1890, 1910-1916.
Arrangement
Arranged into six series:
Series 1. Pauper Accounts, 1809-1917
Series 2. State Board of Charities Letterbooks, 1883-1909
Series 3. Minutes, 1893-1951
Series 4. Secretary's Diary, 1903-1922
Series 5. Reports and Reference Material, 1923-1959
Series 6. Temporary Homes, 1889-1916
Related Material
RG 008 Office of the State Comptroller for pauper records.
RG 061 County Governments for temporary home records.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Board of Charities; Connecticut. Dept. of Social Services; Connecticut. Public Welfare Council; Connecticut. State Welfare Dept.
Subjects:
Children -- Institutional care -- Connecticut; Connecticut. Board of Charities -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. Dept. of Social Services -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. Public Welfare Council -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. State Welfare Dept. -- Records and correspondence; Public welfare -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Account books; Correspondence; Minutes; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Pauper Accounts, 1775-1917; 1954-001; 8 volumes
  - 1775-1777, 1809-1815, 1 volume (Volume Item 1)
    Book in reverse contains a list of payments by the State of Connecticut to the "Port of New London" and the "Coast Guards" for the support and maintenance of troops and fortifications at New London, Stonington and Groton, Oct. 1775 - Jan. 1777.
  - 1815-1824, 1 volume (Volume Item 2)
  - 1877-1883, 1 volume (Volume Item 3)
  - 1883-1887, 1 volume (Volume Item 4)
  - 1887-1896, 1 volume (Volume Item 5)
  - 1897-1906, 1 volume (Volume Item 6)
  - 1906-1910, 1 volume (Volume Item 7)
  - 1910-1917, 1 volume (Volume Item 8)
- Series 2. State Board of Charities letterbooks, 1883-1909; 10 volumes; 1972-001
  - 1883 May 18-1883 December 11, 1 volume (Volume Unnumbered volume)
  - 1885 September 1-1897 April 12, 1 volume (Volume Volume 1)
  - 1897 April 15-1898 May 9, 1 volume (Volume Volume 2)
  - 1898 May 13-1899 April 18, 1 volume (Volume Volume 3)
  - 1899 April 21-1900 April 2, 1 volume (Volume Volume 4)
  - 1900 April 3-1902 January 24, 1 volume (Volume Volume 5)
  - 1902 January 24-1903 July 30, 1 volume (Volume Volume 6)
  - 1903 August 3-1905 May 10, 1 volume (Volume Volume 7)
  - 1905 May 10-1907 August 8, 1 volume (Volume Volume 8)
  - 1907 August 10-1909 May 13, 1 volume (Volume Volume 9)
- Series 3. Minutes, 1893-1951; 1972-002
  - State Board of Charities minutes, 1893-1921 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
  - Department of Public Welfare minutes, 1921 July 16 - 1937 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 9-19)
  - Public Welfare Council minutes, 1937 July 8 - 1951 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - Department of Public Welfare special meeting minutes, 1921-1928 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
    Reverse chronological order
  - Supervisor meeting minutes, 1903-1910 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series 4. Secretary's Diary, 1903-1922; 1972-002
  - Secretary's diary, 1903-1922 (Box 2, Folder 10-14)
- Series 5. Reports and Reference Material, 1923-1959
  - 1972-002 (Box 2)
    - Child welfare (Box 2)
      - Public foster care for dependent and neglected children in Connecticut: a report submitted to the faculty of the School of Social Service Administration in candidacy for the degree of Master of Arts, University of Chicago / by Ruth Catlin Dana, 1946 March; typescript (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Child welfare reports, 1923-1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - Child and the law in Connecticut / Mary Selina Foote, 1923 January (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - History of the development of the program for the supervision of neglected and uncared for children in the state of Connecticut, circa 1954; 3 leaves, typescript (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - Background history of the Connecticut Child Welfare Association, 1957 August; 2 leaves, typescript (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Corrected report of the Public Welfare Council, 1946 June 30; manuscript (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Management study of welfare administration in Connecticut, 1935; typescript (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Organization, structure, and legislation (Box 2)
      - Legislation, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - Reorganization bills affecting departments and institutions, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - Act concerning the Department of Welfare, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - Act concerning the Department of Welfare, 1939; typescript (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Legislation reports (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - Report of the Governor's Committee on Welfare Legislation, 1938 December 16 (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - Report of the Governor's Committee on Welfare Legislation, 1938 December 16; typescript (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - Report of the legislative council, 1952 December 7 (Box 2, Folder 20)
          Public document 96
      - Organizational reports, 1938, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - Organization and administration of the Office of the Commissioner of Public Welfare and the Public Welfare Council State of Connecticut, 1938 / by Carl E. McCombs and L.S. Timmerman, typescript + photocopy (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - Commission on State Government Reorganization final report, Welfare Survey Unit NO. 12, 1949 December (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Papers, 1938-1959 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Report of the Emergency Relief Commission to the Governor, January 1933-June 1934, 1935; typescript (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - Resignation letter of George C.F. Williams as member of Dept. of Public Welfare, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Services to Indians, 1936-1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Special report on relief and reemployment, circa 1938 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 2002-021
    - Collections for care in state mental institutions in Connecticut, 1947; 1 folder (Box shared box)
      Report to the 1947 General Assembly by the Public Welfare Council
- Series 6. Temporary Homes, 1889-1916; 1972-002
  - Litchfield County Temporary Home, Board of Management, record of meetings, 1908 January 7 - 1915 October 8 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - New Haven County Temporary Home, 1889-1916 (Box 3)
    - Record book, 1889-1916; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Labelled "Volume 7"
      Contains secretary's diary, notes, correspondence, etc.
    - Minutes, 1910-1916; 1 volume (Box 3, Folder 3)